A Finding Aid to the Jack Stewart Papers, 1926-2010, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jack Stewart papers
1926-2010
Archives of American Art
Stewart, Jack, 1926-2005
AAA.stewjack
Archival Resource Key
9.9 Linear feet
7.31 Gigabytes
The Jack Stewart papers are dated 1926-2010 and measure 9.9 linear feet and 7.31 GB. A significant portion of the collection concerns Stewart's dissertation, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway" (New York University, 1989), related research, writings, and exhibitions on the subject. Biographical materials, correspondence, writings, printed and digital material, artwork, sketchbooks, and photographic materials document his career as a painter, muralist, designer, educator and administrator.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated in 2010 by Regina Stewart, widow of Jack Stewart.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. This collection is copyright restricted.
Biographical Note
Jack Stewart (1926-2005) was a painter, muralist, designer, educator and administrator in New York City. After developing an interest in graffiti in the 1970s, Stewart eventually wrote a dissertation on the subject, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway" (New York University, 1989) and was recognized as an expert on mass transit art.
Jack Stewart began studying art at the High Museum School in his hometown of Atlanta when he was 10 years old. At age 14, he began a 4 year apprenticeship with painter and sculptor Steffen Thomas. After serving in World War II, he enrolled at Yale University (B.F.A. 1951) as a sculpture student, but soon switched to the painting department where he studied with Josef Albers and Willem de Kooning. After graduation, Stewart began receiving mural commissions and enrolled in classes at Columbia University School of Architecture (1951-1953). His interest in architecture was tied to understanding how to work effectively with architects on mural projects. Later, Stewart developed an interest in graffiti which he pursued through graduate study at New York University (M.A., 1975 and Ph.D., 1989).
Stewart created murals in ceramic tile, mixed media and stained glass. In addition to mosaic murals, he designed tables with mosaic tops. As an outgrowth of his mosaic work, Stewart developed a technique for laminating stained glass onto plate glass that, by eliminating the need for lead, opened new design possibilities. Mural commissions included work for Hamilton Hotel in Chicago, Versailles Hotel in Miami Beach, Public School 28 in New York City, and several ocean liners. The most unusual mural, Raw Material commissioned by Cluett Peabody and Company, was composed of shirt labels embedded in acrylic.
Beginning in 1950 Stewart participated regularly in group shows and enjoyed solo exhibitions mainly in the New York City area. He also showed in Philadelphia, Georgia, Rhode Island, Mexico and Italy, and was included in exhibitions circulated by the American Federation of Arts.
Stewart taught at the college level for nearly thirty years, including: The New School (art and architecture, 1953-1958); Pratt Institute (interior architectural design, 1955-1960); The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art (painting, drawing, human anatomy, art history, 1960-1976; Art Department Chairman, 1971-1976); International Center of Mythymna, American Division, Lesbos, Greece (summer school, 1962-1965); Columbia University (M.F.A. program instructor, 1966-1976); and New York University (drawing, 1967-1975). In 1976 he was appointed Vice President and Provost of the Rhode Island School of Design.
Stewart was active in several professional organizations. He served as New York Artists Equity Association Secretary (1986-1987) and President (1987-1989); President of the National Society of Mural Painters (1996-2000); member of the advisory board of the Steffen Thomas Museum and Archives, Buckhead, GA (1997- 2000s); and President of the Fine Arts Federation of New York (2003-2004). The National Academy of Design elected Jack Stewart an Academician in 1995.
Jack Stewart and Margot Schwarzhaupt, an artist, were married in 1947; they had one son, Brandon. Painter and arts administrator, Regina Serniak, became Jack Stewart's wife in 1976.
Jack Stewart died in New York City in 2005.
Scope and Content Note
The Jack Stewart papers are dated 1926-2010 and measure 9.9 linear feet and 7.31 GB. A significant portion of the collection concerns Stewart's dissertation, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway" (New York University, 1989), related research, writings, and exhibitions on the subject. Biographical materials, correspondence, writings, printed and digital material, artwork, sketchbooks, and photographic materials document his career as a painter, muralist, designer, educator and administrator.
Biographical materials include a "Video Archive" in digital format, consisting mainly of Jack Stewart being interviewed on several occasions by Nancy Gold for her television show, "What It Takes." In addition to discussions about Stewart's career, the shows include examples of his paintings and murals along with views of him at work.
Correspondence mostly documents Stewart's artistic career and work as an educator and administrator; there is some personal correspondence, as well. Of particular note are letters to Rodman Townsend who commissioned a mural about the human brain; they discuss the details of the project and its evolution, brain research, and subsequent exhibitions of related paintings. Illustrated letters and greeting cards with original artwork are from Violet Baxter, Lorrie Goulet, Wolf Kahn, Clare Romano, Anthony Toney, and Sam Weiner. Herbert Brooks Walker sent several pieces of mail art and, while in Italy, collected graffiti information for Stewart. Letters Stewart wrote to his mother span decades; the best represented periods are the years he served in the U.S. Army and studied at Yale University.
Writings and notes consist of Stewart's dissertation ("Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway"), miscellaneous writings and notes, and art and architecture notebooks. Dissertation documentation includes the manuscript, drafts, and related records. Among the miscellaneous writings and notes - published and unpublished - are shorter pieces, articles, student papers, and teaching notes. Of particular interest are notes/instructions for a performance piece titled "Endless Subway," "Memories of Steffan Thomas" and "My Recollection of Charles Egan." Also found are minutes of Cooper Union adjunct faculty meetings (1965-1966), and reports written when provost of the Rhode Island School of Design. Art and architecture notebooks (5 volumes) were compiled while at Yale University.
Research files on graffiti contain many sound recordings and some transcripts of interviews with graffiti writers, voluminous lists of graffiti writers' names/tags, correspondence, notes, photographs, and a wide variety of printed material. Some of the material is in digital format. Stewart began collecting these materials as his interest in graffiti developed. They were used for his dissertation and material continued to be added after the dissertation was completed.
Printed material mentioning Stewart or containing reproductions of his work includes exhibition catalogs, posters, and newsletters.
Artwork by Jack Stewart consists of drawings, paintings, and one etching; also found are designs and plans for tables, murals, and other projects. Drawings include figure studies, heads, and landscapes; most are in pencil and some in ink. The small number of paintings are oil on canvas (removed from stretchers), and gouache on paper and board. Sketchbooks (44 volumes) contain mostly pencil drawings and sketches, and a few studies for paintings and murals. Two volumes include writings about travels and events; of particular interest are "Notes on Kline's funeral May 1962," "Visit to Roman Bronze Art Foundry," and "Notes on My Development."
Photographic materials consist mainly photographs, but also include digital images and 35-mm color slides. Images of Stewart include views of him with paintings and working in his studio. Identified individuals with whom he appears are: Regina Stewart (wife), Brandon Stewart (son), Lil Stewart (mother), Ninalee Craig, Irving Sandler, and students in Urbino, Italy. Photographs of artwork document murals such as Raw Material (composed of shirt labels), and Versailles Hotel in Miami Beach; among the paintings documented are State of the Union, Icons of Western Art and Revelation XVI-16 (both with keys to individuals portrayed). Exhibition openings and installations are shown in photographs, color slides, and video recordings. Also found are photographs of the World Trade Center site taken by Stewart in December 2001.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 9 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1926-circa 2009 (Boxes 1,11; 0.6 linear foot, ER01-ER02, 3.92 GB)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1944-2009 (Boxes 1-2; 0.7 linear foot)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1947-2003 (Boxes 2-5; 3.1 linear foot)
Series 4: Research Files on Graffiti, 1972-2010 (Boxes 5-7,11; 2.8 linear foot, ER03-ER05, 3.18 GB)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1945-2002 (Boxes 8, 11, OV 13; 0.7 linear foot)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, circa 1990-2003 (Box 8; 0.2 linear foot)
Series 7: Artwork, 1946-2000 (Boxes 8, 11, OV 12; 0.3 linear foot)
Series 8: Sketchbooks, 1951-2004 (Boxes 8-9; 1.3 linear foot)
Series 9: Photographic Materials, circa 1950s-2010 (Boxes 10-11; 0.4 linear foot, ER06-ER07, 0.208 GB)
Related Materials
Jack Stewart papers, 1926-2015, are located at Emory University Stuart A. Rose Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library.
Drawings; Sound recordings; Paintings; Street art; Sketchbooks; Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Interviews; Mail art; Transcripts; Art -- Study and teaching; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Graffiti art; Video recordings; Arts administrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Designers -- New York (State) -- New York; New York City Transit Authority; Thomas, Steffen, 1906-; Kahn, Wolf, 1927-; Townsend, Rodman; Romano, Clare; Toney, Anthony; Egan, Charles, 1911-; Weiner, Sam; Baxter, Violet; Walker, Herbert Brooks, 1927-; Goulet, Lorrie, 1925-; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.); Gold, Nancy; Yale University -- Students
- Biographical Materials, 1926-circa 2009; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1, 11; 3.92 Gigabytes ER01-ER02
  Scope and Contents
  Stewart's 75th birthday celebration at The Broom Street Gallery is recorded on a videocassette (VHS) and also exists in digital format. Extensive information about family history, much of it compiled in the 1980s by Stewart's aunt and Travis Burns (nephew?) is included in "Lil: In Celebration of Lillie Ruth Hemperley Stewart's 99th Birthday, February 16, 2004" by Regina Stewart. Financial records consist of commissions and prices paid by decorators for mosaic murals, tables, and miscellaneous items. Legal documents include a birth certificate, U.S. Army honorable discharge papers; also found is certification of Stewart as an artist, allowing him to reside in his loft studio. The "Video Archive" in digital format includes several television interviews with Stewart that include many views and discussion of his work.
  Arrangement
  This series is alphabetized by folder title.
  - Addresses, Phone Numbers, Messages, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes and Resume, 1963-circa 2009; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "A Birthday Celebration for Jack Stewart, The Broome Street Gallery", 2001 January 30; Archival Resource Key; 1 video cassette: VHS; includes born-digital records, see ER01. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jack Stewart Drawings: Looking into the 21st Century, a film by Harriet Spalding (2002), Digital Video Recording, 2009; Archival Resource Key; 0.112 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER01)
  - Certificates, 1946-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Childhood Memorabilia, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - "Babyhood Days", 1926-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Binky Smith" Comic Strip, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Elementary School Newspaper, Jack Stewart, Art Editor, circa 1934-1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - High School Notebooks, undated; 1941-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - High School TrackTeam, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - High School Yearbook Advertisement, 1943; Archival Resource Key; Oversized material housed in Box 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - High School Yearbook, Alciphronian, Boys' High School, Atlanta, GA, 1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Diplomas, 1931-1989; Archival Resource Key; Oversized material housed in Box 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Family History, 2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Financial Records, 1955-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Identification and Membership Cards, undated; 1968-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Legal Documents, 1942-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Passports, Vaccination Certificates, International Driving Permits, 1962-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 10th Annual Ocean Grove Memorial Day Art Event, 1991; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Video Archive, Digital Video Recording, circa 1989-2010; Archival Resource Key; 3.81 Gigabytes One computer file; Videos included: Installation of an unidentified modular mosaic mural (undated); Interview of Jack Stewart, TV News, CBS News 2, New York City (circa 1990); The Nature of Clouds, lecture by Jack Stewart (26 May, 1991); Interviews with Nancy Gold on What It Takes TV program (circa 1989-1992). (Folder ER02)
  - Oversized Biographical Material from Box 1, Folder 6, 11, 13, circa 1938-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
- Correspondence, 1944-2009; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence largely documents Stewart's professional activities; some purely personal letters are included, as well. Among the correspondents are galleries and museums, clients, publishers, universities, professional organizations, family, and friends. Correspondence post-dating Stewart's lifetime concerns donations of artwork and publication of his writings.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name or institution. Among the writings and notes (Series 3) is additional correspondence concerning Stewart's dissertation, and a book proposal for "Letters to Leaders from an Artist" (1992-1999) that may include copies of letters that do not appear also in this series. Also, a fair amount of correspondence is scattered throughout the research files on graffiti (Series 4).
  - AARP - Atlanta History Center, 1960-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Baltimore Sun - Bush, George W., 1971-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Candell, Victor - Columbia Museum of Art, 1967-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Columbia University, 1967-1978, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Committee to Support the President - Conte, Frank M., 1974-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, 1961-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Corning Museum of Glass - Frankenthaler, Helen, 1961-1998; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gallery and Studio - Gwinnett Council for the Arts, 1963-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Heery and Heery Architects - Inoue, Izumi, undated; 1959-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - International Institute of Language and the Arts, undated; 1964-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jessica Dee Communications, Inc. - Lowrance, Mr. and Mrs. Richard, undated; 1959-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Magnus, Dieter - Museum of the City of New York, undated; 1962-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - National Academy of Design - National Endowment for the Arts, 1989-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - National Society of Mural Painters - New York Transit Museum, 1961-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - New York University, undated; 1967-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Nuell, Lon - Philadelphia Museum of Art, undated; 1957-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Powers, Steve - Pyneburg, Henk, 1959-2008; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The Queens Museum - Sullivan, Rich, undated; 1959-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Stewart, Mrs. Jack T. (mother), 1944-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39-42)
  - Stewart, Regina (wife) - Toney, Anthony, undated; 1975-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Townsend, Rodman, 1984-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Travers, David B. V. - Vickrey, Bob and Marje, undated; 1946-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Walker, Herbert Brooks, 1963-2002; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Watson, Frank E. - Watson-Guptil Publications, 1962-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Weiner, Sam, 1984-2004; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Weiss, Sonya - Zappala, Rosalie, 1946-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified, 1961-1999; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1947-2003; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 3.1 Linear feet Boxes 2-5
  The dissertation manscript and various drafts are followed by related files, arranged alphabetically. Miscellaneous writings are arranged in rough chronological order. Additional writings are found in a few sketchbooks (Series 8).
  All writings are by Jack Stewart. There are drafts, related correspondence, notes and photocredits, as well as the completed manuscript of his dissertation, "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway System of New York City, 1970-1978" (New York University, 1989). Miscellaneous writings and notes, published and unpublished, include shorter pieces, articles, student papers, and teaching notes. Of particular interest are notes/instructions for a performance piece titled "Endless Subway," "Memories of Steffan Thomas" and "My Recollections of Charles Egan." Also found are minutes of Cooper Union adjunct faculty meetings, and reports written when Stewart was Provost of the Rhode Island School of Design. Art and architectuure notebooks were compiled while Stewart was a student at Yale.
  - Dissertation, circa 1970s-circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Manuscript, "An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway System of New York City, 1970-1978,", 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - "Subway Graffiti: An Aesthetic Study of Graffiti on the Subway System of New York City, 1970-1978," University Microfilms International, circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Drafts, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
    - Abstract, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Appendices, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, New York University and UMI Dissertation Abstracts, 1975-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, Research, 1982-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Notes, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Photo Credits, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Photographs, circa 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Proposal, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes, 1960s-2003; Archival Resource Key
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes including Mass Transit Art Film Proposal, Artist's Statements and "Conceptual Development of My Art,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Writings and Notes about Indian Temples, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Certain Relationships between the Mosaics of Ravenna and Venice,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Certain Symbolic Aspects of the Kailasantha Temple at Ellora, India, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Circumambulating the Kailasantha Temple at Ellora, India" and "The Importance of Glass through the Centuries,", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes including "Endless Subway," Travel Diary and Trip Expenses, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Minutes of Cooper Union Adjunct Faculty Meetings, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Writings and Notes on Drawing, Color, and Travel Itinerary, 1970-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Student Notes, N.Y.U., 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Teaching Notes; Student Paper, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "The Paterson Lyric Opera Theatre: A History," Volumes 1-3, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    - "Concepts of Intelligence: A Study of the Structure of Intellect Model," circa 1975, Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Notes on History of Mosaics; Student Paper, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Reports of Provost to Board of Trustees, Rhode Island School of Design, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Son of the Six Thousand Year Old Rakshasa,", circa 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Graphics Techniques: Intaglio;" Remarks on Colossal Sculpture, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous Writings and Notes including Articles on Films about Artists, Drawing, and "Mass Transit Art,", 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Writing and Notes including Proposal for "Murals in the Making," "Memories of Steffan Thomas," autobiographical notes, and sound cassette of "Arts Breaking," Feb. 4, 1993 WBAI Radio Program, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key; Includes 1 sound cassette (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Letters to Leaders from an Artist" (1992-1999), circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Writings including Lecture Text, List of Paintings for 2000 Blue Hill Exhibition, and "My Recollection of Charles Egan,", 2000-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Portfolio, "Selected Artworks of Jack Stewart, Ph.D., NA,", 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Art and Architecture Notebooks, circa 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key
    - Art 10, (Prehistory - 16th century), circa 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Art 10, (16th century - 19th century), circa 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Architecture 10a (Overview; Egyptian - Moorish), circa 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Architecture 10b, part 1 (Fall of Rome - Gothic), circa 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Architecture 10b, part 2 (Renaissance - 20th century), circa 1947-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Research Files on Graffiti, 1972-2010; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 2.8 Linear feet Boxes 5-7,11; 3.18 Gigabytes ER03-ER05